Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts, late 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0776
Manuscripts Division
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 43: Miracles of Mary (Tä'ammərä Maryam) and Miracles of Saint George (Tä'amərä Giyorgis), 1700s; 2 cols. [fols. 1r-67v], 19 lines; 3 columns [fols. 68r-77v]), 21 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. No wooden boards, leather cover, stitch
  - Miracles of Mary, 1700s; Located on folio 1r-67v. (Unitid 43)
    - First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 1rv. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Barok, a dissolute man (incomplete) (Budge, Mary, 26; Strelcyn 32.16.26).
    - Introductory Rite from Mu'alləqa (Incomplete At the Beginning), 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 2r-4v. (Unitid 43)
    - Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 4v-6v. (Unitid 43)
    - Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 6v-8r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Anəsətasəyos) (Budge, Mary, 27; Strelcyn 32.16.27).
    - Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 8rv. (Unitid 43)
    - Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 8v-9v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the Jew of Akəmim, an elderly priest, when he fell and broke his back during his service in her church (incomplete at the ending, folio missing) (Budge, Mary, 03).
    - Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 10r-11r. (Unitid 43)
      How Marəqos, King of Rome, fled from his palace for the monastery for the love of the Virgin Mary.
    - Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 11r-12r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to the dying monk in the island of Tigris.
    - Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 12r-13r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to the widow and commanded her to recite the "Hail Mary" (Budge, Mary, ?).
    - Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 13rv. (Unitid 43)
    - Tenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 13v-14v. (Unitid 43)
    - Eleventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 14v-15v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain woman on the altar of the monastery.
    - Twelfth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 15v-17r. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 17r-18v. (Unitid 43)
    - Fourteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 18v-20r. (Unitid 43)
      How the icon of the Virgin Mary in a certain church bowed to the young person who served in the church and when he bowed to her (Budge, Mary, 104, for a different version).
    - Fifteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 20v-21v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary saved from death a governor of Eferan named Armatəyas.
    - Sixteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 21v-22v. (Unitid 43)
    - Seventeenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 22v-23v. (Unitid 43)
    - Eighteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 23v-25r. (Unitid 43)
    - Nineteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 25r-26r. (Unitid 43)
    - Twentieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 26r-27v. (Unitid 43)
    - Twenty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 27v-29r. (Unitid 43)
    - Twenty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 29r-30r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared out of her picture to Mary, the daughter of a certain God-fearing man from Dafra, to give her communion and promised to take her to Paradise after three days (Budge, Mary, 7).
    - Twenty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 30rv. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary carried a sick person from the Monastery of the Pilgrims to Jerusalem and showed him where Jesus was crucified and buried and baptized him in the waters of the Jordan) (Budge, Mary, 9; Strelcyn 32.16.9).
    - Twenty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 30v-32v. (Unitid 43)
    - Twenty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 32v-33r. (Unitid 43)
    - Twenty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 33r-34v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary saved two Muslims from the storm when they called on her name (Budge, Mary, 12; Strelcyn 32.16. 12).
    - Twenty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 34v-36r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the eyes of Yohannəs Bäkänəsi, the blind priest in Egypt, by anointing him with milk from her breasts (Budge, Mary, 14; Strelcyn 32.16.14).
    - Twenty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 36r-37r. (Unitid 43)
    - Twenty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 37r-38v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary restored the sight of Elizabeth, a blind girl, with her breath and milk (Budge, Mary, 16; Strelcyn 32.16. 16).
    - Thirtieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 38v-39r. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 39r-40r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the foot of a widow from Harətärom) (Budge, Mary, 24).
    - Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 40r-43r. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 43r-44v. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 44v-45r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary healed Bishop Märqorəwos of his leprosy (Budge, Mary, 23; Strelcyn 32.16.23).
    - Thirty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 45r-46v. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 46v-49v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary aided in the delivery of a child to an abbess before the bishop came to enquire into the matter (Budge, Mary, 25; Strelcyn 32.16.25).
    - Thirty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 49v-50v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary cut out and sewed a garment for Filatawos, a bishop of the city of Sä'id in Upper Egypt (Budge, Mary,40).
    - Thirty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 50v-51v. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 51v-52v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary moved the Monastery of Ekona (Budge, Mary, 13; Strelcyn 32.16. 13).
    - Fortieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 52v-53v. (Unitid 43)
      How Abba Samu'el levitated from the ground and spewed fire from his mouth and was not touched by the rain when he read the praises of the Virgin Mary (not in Budge).
    - Forty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 53v-55v. (Unitid 43)
    - Forty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 55v-57r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary and Jesus and the Angels came to Pifamon before his martyrdom (not in Budge).
    - Forty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 57r-58r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary helped a Roman prefect when a mysterious ram prevented him from visiting Christ's tomb until he had become a follower of the Virgin Mary (Budge, Mary, 39).
    - Forty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 58r-61r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary rebuked a woman who gave up fasting at her husband's command (Budge, Mary, 99).
    - Forty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 61rv. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary delivered from prison a certain man called Giyorgis (Budge, Mary, 19; Strelcyn 32.16. 19).
    - Forty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 61v-62v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary protected the elderly priest called Qätir from the church door keeper by paralyzing the keeper (Budge, Mary, 20; Strelcyn 32.16. 20).
    - Forty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 62v-63v. (Unitid 43)
    - Forty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 63v-65r. (Unitid 43)
      How a certain rich man hurled a loaf at the head of a beggar and wounded him, and how the Virgin Mary delivered his soul from the devils) (Budge, Mary, 86).
    - Forty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 65r-67v. (Unitid 43)
  - Miracles of Saint George, 1700s; Located on folio 68r-77r. (Unitid 43)
    - First Miracle of Saint George, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 68r. (Unitid 43)
      How Saint Giyorgis appeared to Awəlogis and gave him a ship full of riches (incomplete at the beginning, see 75r-77v for the beginning).
    - Second Miracle of Saint George, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 68r-71v. (Unitid 43)
      How Saint Giyorgis removed a priest from his ministry who had stolen a gift from the church and how he saved the priest from his sins.
      Second Miracle of Saint George is in a different hand.
    - Third Miracle of Saint George, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 71v-73v. (Unitid 43)
      How Saint Giyorgis appeared as a builder to help the construction of the church in Ləda during the reign of Constantine.
    - Fourth Miracle of Saint George, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 73v-75r. (Unitid 43)
      How Saint Giyorgis punished Awyan, the commander of Dəyoqəltyanos, when he destroyed the Church of St George in Jerusalem.
    - Fifth Miracle of Saint George, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 75r-77v. (Unitid 43)
      How Saint Giyorgis appeared to Awəlogis and gave him a ship full of riches (incomplete at the end, see 68r for the end of the miracle).
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 44: Synaxarium (Lives of the Saints). Sənksar, early 19th century; 3 cols., 33 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Wooden boards bound in stamped red leather, covered spine. Fols. 2rv, 228rv: Blank. Fols. 65rv: Quarter folio (Unitid 44)
  Fol. 1r: Arabic numbers "2146," "183"; illegible Amharic words in pencil.
  Fol. 1v: Note of ownership in later hand in colored pencil "This synaxarium belongs to Däbrä Qədusan." Followed by two lines in Amharic in the same hand: "any person who reads this or listens may become a righteous person. The scribe is Aläqqa Esäy."
  At the end of every daily entry, the name Wäldä Micha'el appears in the original text.
  Owner: Wäldä Micha'el.
  No scribe listed in original manuscript.
  References: Regarding the Ethiopic Synaxarium, see Conti Rossini, Manoscritti ed opere abissinein Europa, Rendiconti della Reale Accademia dei Lincei, vol. Viii, 1889, p.630. H.Zotenberg, Catalogue des manuscrits éthiopiens (gheez et amharique de la Bibliotheque Nationale, Paris 1877. No.126 and 128,pp.152-95; S. Grébaut et E. Tisserant, Codices aethiopici Vaticani et Borgiaani Barberinianus Orientalis 2, Rossianus 865, Città del Vaticano, (1935-36) No. 111 -112; Strelcyn.(B.M). 54; EMML 4273; 4274.
  - Sənksar (Synaxarium for the Second Half of the Year), early 19th century; Located on folio 3r-227v. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Mäggabit, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 3r-38v. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Miyazya, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 39r-65v. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Gənbot, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 66r-104r. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Säne, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 104r-140v. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Hamle, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 141r-186v. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Nähase, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 186v-221r. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Pagwame, early 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 221v-227v. (Unitid 44)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 45: Synaxarium (Lives of the Saints). Sənksar, circa 1730-1899; 3 cols., varies due to repairs, but mostly 34 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Wooden boards missing, parchment cover, stitched and open spine. fols. 1r, 35v, 103v, 192v: Blank. Some folios were quarter or half folios. The top right quarter of almost all folios (1v-192v) appears to have been damaged, seemingly by fire. It was repaired by cutting away those sections from each folio and sewing new pieces in. The new portions are in another hand. Sometimes the scribes had to squeeze text to make it fit. The repairs were probably done in the late 1800s. (Unitid 45)
  Fol. 225v: Ge'ez alphabet with Ethiopic numbers.
  Fol. 226r: Ge'ez alphabet in pencil.
  Fol. 226v: Pen trial.
  At the end of every daily entry appear the names of the manuscript owners / benefactors Wäldä Häwarəyat and Fasilädäs.
  Fol. 1v: In another hand, that of the sewn-in-portions of the folios, is a scribal note: "Praise to God, the Lord of Michael [the Archangel], who enabled us to finish this book without weariness or exhaustion, without sickness or distress, with joy and peace. The scribe of this book is Gəra Geta [church title] Hayəlu Hayəlä Micha'el with his son Gəra Geta Därsäh Gäbrä Həywät. Do not forget us in your prayers."
  References: See references listed in manuscript no. 44.
  - Sənksar (Synaxarium for the First Half of the Year), circa 1730-1899; Located on folio 2r-225vv. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Mäskäräm, circa 1730-1899; 1 item Located on folio 2r-35r. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Təqəmt, circa 1730-1899; 1 item Located on folio 36r-66r. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Hədar, circa 1730-1899; 1 item Located on folio 67r-103r. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Tahəśaś, circa 1730-1899; 1 item Located on folio 104r-145v. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Tərr, circa 1730-1899; 1 item Located on folio 146r-192r. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Yäkkatit, circa 1730-1899; 1 item Located on folio 193r-225v. (Unitid 45)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 46: Miracles of Mary (Tä'ammərä Maryam), late 17th century; 3 cols., 27 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. One wooden board covered in stamped leather, stitched and open spine, lower board missing. Cloth on inside cover. Fol. 1r: Erased, upside down six-line note. Folio is not part of quire, but a folded single piece of parchment. Fols. 2rv, 8v, 32v: Blank. fol. 166v: The last miracle is incomplete, at least one folio is missing (Unitid 46)
  Fol. 125r: The "King of Ethiopia" is mentioned, but not his name.
  Most of the miracles in this manuscript take place in Egyptian monasteries.
  At the beginning of each miracle, the name of one of the manuscript's benefactors or owners is mentioned. Most of the time the names Wäldä Yahannəs and Arkä Giyorəgis alternate. Sometimes the names Wäldä Giyorəgis and Gedewon appear. From fol. 6r to fol. 43r, the owner's name has been erased.
  Owners: Wäldä Yahannəs, Arkä Giyorəgis, Wäldä Giyorəgis, Gedewon.
  References: See references for manuscript no. 8.
  - Introductory Rite from Mu'alləqa, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 3r-7r. (Unitid 46)
  - Prayer to the Virgin Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 7r-8r. (Unitid 46)
  - First Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 9r-10r. (Unitid 46)
  - Second Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 10rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to the dying monk in island of Tigris (not in Budge).
  - Third Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 10v-11r. (Unitid 46)
  - Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 11rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary healed the Jew of Akəmim, an elderly priest, when he fell and broke his back during his service in her church (Budge, Mary, 3).
  - Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 11v-12v. (Unitid 46)
  - Sixth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 12v-13r. (Unitid 46)
  - Seventh Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 13r-14r. (Unitid 46)
  - Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 14rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared out of her picture to Mary, the daughter of a certain God-fearing man, and promised to take her to Paradise after three days (Budge, Mary, 7; Strelcyn 32.16.7).
  - Ninth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 14v-15v. (Unitid 46)
    How a painter was saved by the Virgin Mary when he fell from a scaffold (Budge, Mary, 8, Strelcyn ?).
  - Tenth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 15v-16r. (Unitid 46)
  - Eleventh Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 16r-17r. (Unitid 46)
  - Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 17rv. (Unitid 46)
    Miracle of Mary (How the Virgin Mary recovered the stolen property of two women called Juliana and Barbara, when they were on pilgrimage to Jerusalem (Budge, Mary, 11; Strelcyn 32.16. 11).
  - Twelfth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 17r-18v. (Unitid 46)
  - Thirteenth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 18rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary moved the Monastery of Ekona (Budge, Mary, 13; Strelcyn 32.16. 13)
  - Fourteenth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 19rv. (Unitid 46)
  - Fifteenth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 19v-20r. (Unitid 46)
  - Sixteenth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 20r-21r. (Unitid 46)
  - Seventeenth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 21rv. (Unitid 46)
  - Eighteenth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 21v-22r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary delivered the soul of the scribe who was writing the book of her miracles (Budge, Mary, 18; Strelcyn 32.16.18).
  - Nineteenth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 22rv. (Unitid 46)
  - Twentieth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 22v-23r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary protected the elderly priest called Qätir (Budge, Mary, 20; Strelcyn 32.16. 20).
  - Twenty-First Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 23r-24r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary sent Saint George to threaten a Qädi (Islamic leader) for imprisoning a Christian (Budge, Mary, 21; Strelcyn 32.16.21).
  - Twenty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 24rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary healed a man with a stone foot (Budge, Mary, 22; Strelcyn 32.16.22).
  - Twenty-Third Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 24v-25r. (Unitid 46)
  - Twenty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 25rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to a person in the church Haratälom.
  - Twenty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 25v-27r. (Unitid 46)
  - Twenty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 27rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Barok, a dissolute man (Budge, Mary, 26; Strelcyn 32.16.26).
  - Twenty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 27v-28r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Anəsətasəyos (Budge, Mary, 27; Strelcyn 32.16.27).
  - Twenty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 28r-29v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary helped a monk to escape the monastery of Qäləmon when persecuted by other monks (Budge, Mary, 28; Strelcyn 32.16.28).
  - Twenty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 29v-30v. (Unitid 46)
  - Thirtieth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 30v-31v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary delivered a thief, the son of a poor widow (Budge, Mary, 30).
  - Thirty-First Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 31v-32r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary saved the woman in childbirth from drowning (Budge, Mary, 32; Strelcyn 32.16. 31; Bland 2, also Vincent de Beauvais (from 1264)).
  - Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 33r-34v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to Abraham, Archbishop of Alexandria when he was challenged by a Jews and Muslims to move a mountain.
  - Thirty-Third Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 34v-40r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary saved a church in Adrem from destruction by the Caliph.
  - Thirty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 40r-41r. (Unitid 46)
    How Saint Maridari received the blessing of the angels.
  - Thirty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 41rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary as a bird appeared to a wealthy person.
  - Thirty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 41v-42v. (Unitid 46)
    How St Paul saw the glory of the Virgin Mary in heaven.
  - Thirty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 42v-43r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to Abba Bəhor, the disciple of Abba Amani.
  - Thirty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 43r-44r. (Unitid 46)
    How Gregory heard about the glory of the Virgin Mary.
  - Thirty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 44rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary helped Säwla, wife of Giyorgis (the new martyr) when she wanted to bury the remain of her husband's body.
  - Fortieth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 44v-45r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared every year on the 21st of the month of Ter near the Jordan river.
  - Forty-First Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 45rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary saved the children of the magician named Abrasit.
  - Forty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 45v-46r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to the noble man and healed his son.
  - Forty-Third Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 46rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary healed the woman blinded by a demon.
  - Forty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 46v-47r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to the Archishop Tewate.
  - Forty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 47r-48v. (Unitid 46)
  - Forty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 48v-49r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to Saint Anthony about the monastery.
  - Forty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 49r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to the Saint Anthony to tell the archbishop Timothy to construct a church in her name.
  - Forty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 49v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary anointed and healed the animals, according to Saint Anthony.
  - Forty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 49v-50v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to Saint Anthony and told him why she anointed the animals.
  - Fiftieth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 50v-51v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to Saint Anthony carrying the bottle of oil.
  - Fifty-First Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 51v-53v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to Timothy the Archbishop.
  - Fifty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 53r. (Unitid 46)
    How Saint John the golden-mouthed received the key to the kingdom of heaven.
  - Fifty-Third Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 53v-54r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Jewish leaders tried to burn the home of the Virgin Mary.
  - Fifty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 54rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Holy Spirit taught the disciples about the honor of the Sunday services.
  - Fifty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; 1 item Located on folio 54v-55v. (Unitid 46)